Earlier in this lesson,
在这节课的早些时候
we looked at how the key concept of attention is to calculate an attention weight vector,
我们了解了注意力的关键概念是计算注意力权重向量
which is used to amplify the signal from
用来放大来自输入序列
the most relevant parts of the input sequence and in the same time,
最相关部分的信号
drown out the irrelevant parts.
同时忽略不相关部分
In this video, we'll begin to look at
在这个视频中
the scoring functions that produce these attention weights.
我们将讲解生成这些注意力权重的评分函数
An attention scoring function tends to be a function that takes in
注意力评分函数会接受编码器的隐藏状态
the hidden state of the decoder and the set of hidden states of the encoder.
以及解码器的一组隐藏状态
Since this is something we'll do at each timestep on the decoder side,
因为对于解码器来说 我们将在每个时间步执行这一计算
we only use the hidden state of the decoder at
因此仅使用该时间步的解码器隐藏状态
that timestep or the previous timestep in some scoring methods.
或者在某些评分函数中使用上个时间步的解码器隐藏状态
Given these two inputs,
给定这两个输入
this vector and this matrix,
这个向量和这个矩阵
it produces a vector that scores each of these columns.
它会生成对每列评分的向量
Before looking at the matrix version,
在查看矩阵版本之前
which calculates the scores for all the encoder hidden states in one step,
即计算一个时间步所有编码器隐藏状态的得分
let's simplify it by looking at how to score a single encoder hidden state.
我们先简化下 了解如何对单个编码器隐藏状态评分
The first scoring method and the simplest is to
第一个评分函数 也是最简单的函数
just calculate the dot product of the two input vectors.
将计算这两个输入向量的点积
The dot product of two vectors produces a single number, so that's good.
两个向量的点积生成一个数字 不错
But the important thing is the significance of this number.
但是重要的是这个数字的显著性
Geometrically, the dot product of two vectors is equal to
从几何角度来讲 两个向量的点积
multiplying the lengths of the two vectors by the cosine of the angle between them,
等于将两个向量的长度乘以夹角的余弦
and we know that cosine has
我们知道余弦有个很方便的特性
this convenient property that it equals one if the angle is zero and it decreases,
如果夹角为 0 则余弦为 1
the wider the angle becomes.
夹角越大 余弦越小
What this means is that if we have two vectors with the same length,
意味着 如果两个向量的长度一样
the smaller the angle between them,
夹角越小
the larger the dot product becomes.
点积越大
This dot product is a similarity measure between vectors.
这个点积衡量的是两个向量的相似性
The dot product produces a larger number,
如果点积越大
the smaller the angle between the vectors are.
则表明向量夹角越小
In practice, however, we want to speed up the calculation
但是 在实际操作中 我们希望通过
by scoring all the encoder hidden states at once,
一次性对所有编码器隐藏状态评分加快计算流程
which leads us to the formal mathematical definition of dot product attention.
这就得出了点积注意力的正式数学定义
That's what we have here.
即这一部分
It is the hidden state of the current timestep transposed
它是当前时间步的隐藏状态转置后
times the matrix of the encoder hidden timesteps.
乘以编码器隐藏时间步的矩阵
That looks like this and that will produce the vector of the scores.
看起来是这样的 生成得分向量
With the simplicity of this method comes the drawback of assuming
简化这个方法就会导致一个缺点
the encoder and decoder have the same embedding space.
即假设编码器和解码器具有相同的嵌入空间
So, while this might work for text summarization, for example,
虽然这个方法适用于文本摘要
where the encoder and decoder use the same language and the same embedding space.
其中编码器和解码器使用相同的语言和嵌入空间
For machine translation, however,
但是对于机器翻译来说
you might find that each language tends to have its own embedding space.
你会发现每种语言都有自己的嵌入空间
This is a case where we might want to use the second scoring method,
这时候可能就要用到第二种评分函数了
which is a slight variation on the first.
它对第一种函数稍加修改
It simply introduces a weight matrix between
将编码器隐藏状态和
the multiplication of the decoder hidden state and the encoder hidden states.
解码器隐藏状态相乘 引入权重矩阵
This weight matrix is a linear transformation that allows the inputs and outputs to use
这个权重矩阵是线性转换 允许输入和输出使用不同的嵌入
different embeddings and the result of this multiplication would be the weights vector.
这个乘法的结果是权重向量
Let us now look back at this animation
我们再回到这个动画
and incorporate everything that we know about attention.
并包含关于注意力的所有知识
The first time step in the attention decoder starts by taking
注意力解码器的第一个时间步
an initial hidden state as well as the embedding for the end symbol.
首先获得初始隐藏状态和结束符号的嵌入
It does its calculation and generates the hidden state at that timestep and here,
它进行计算并生成该时间步的隐藏状态
we are ignoring the actual outputs of the RNN,
这里 我们将忽略 RNN 的实际输出
we're just using the hidden states.
只使用隐藏状态
Then we do our attention step.
然后是注意力步骤
We do that by taking in the matrix of the hidden states of the encoder.
获取编码器隐藏状态矩阵
We produce a scoring as we've mentioned.
像之前提到的那样 生成得分
So, if we're doing multiplicative attention,
如果执行乘法注意力运算
we'll use the dot product.
则使用点积
In general, we produce the scores,
总之 生成得分
we do a softmax,
应用 softmax
we multiply the softmax scores by each corresponding hidden state from the encoder,
将 softmax 得分与编码器中的每个相应隐藏状态相乘
we sum them up producing our attention context vector and then what we do next is this,
求和 生成注意力语境向量
we concatenate the attention context vector
下一步是将注意力语境向量
with the hidden state of a decoder at that timestep so h4.
与该时间步的解码器隐藏状态（即 h4）相连
So this would be c4 concatenated with h4,
也就是 c4 与 h4 相连
that's what we will do here.
即这里的步骤
So, we basically glued them together as one vector and then we pass them through
将它们合并成一个向量
a fully connected neural network which is basically
然后将它们传入一个完全连接的神经网络
multiplying by the weights matrix WC and apply a tanh activation.
也就是乘以权重矩阵 wc 应用双曲正切激活函数
The output of this fully connected layer would be
这个完全连接层的输出
our first outputted word in the output sequence.
将是输出序列中的第一个输出单词
We can now proceed to the second step,
现在进入下一步
passing the hidden state to it and taking the output from the first decoder timestep.
将隐藏状态传递给它 并接受第一个解码器时间步的输出
We produce h5, we start our attention at this step as well, we score,
生成 h5 在这个时间步也执行注意力运算 评分
we produce a weights vector,
生成权重向量
we do softmax, we multiply,
应用 softmax 相乘
we add them up producing c5.
相加 生成 c5
The attention context vector at step five,
得出第五步的注意力语境向量
we glue it together with the hidden state,
将它与隐藏状态合并
we pass it through the same fully-connected network with tanh activation producing
传入相同的完全连接网络并应用双曲正切激活函数
the second word in our output and this goes on
生成输出中的第二个单词 一直持续下去
until we have completed outputting the output sequence.
直到完成输出序列
This is pretty much the full view of how attention works in sequence-to-sequence models.
这就是序列到序列模型中的注意力原理的完整流程图
In the next video, we'll touch on additive attention.
在下个视频中 我们将讲解加法注意力